<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: brewing | Mike DeLaurentis]]></title>
  <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/categories/brewing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-25T21:27:09-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike DeLaurentis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Oatmeal Stout]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/10/28/Oatmeal-Stout/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/10/28/Oatmeal-Stout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After a a couple batches that I wasn't totally happy with, I I like this one a lot. Similar creamy mouthfeel to the Rye
Porter. Pretty dry, not much hop aroma or flaver. Very nice roasty
character.</p>

<h2>Grains</h2>

<ul>
<li>11 lbs American 2-Row Pale</li>
<li>1 lb Crystal 60</li>
<li>1/2 lb Chocolate Malt</li>
<li>1/2 lb Roasted Barley</li>
<li>2 lbs Flaked Oats</li>
</ul>


<h2>Hops</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 oz Nugget (15.1%), 60 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Willamette (3.6%), 30 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Willamette (3.6%), 15 mins</li>
</ul>


<h2>Process</h2>

<p>Single infusion mash at 154 &deg;.  Expected water loss due to absorption: 1.5 gal. Total mash/lauter water: 8 gal. Target pre-boil vol: 6.5 gal. Strike vol: 15 lbs x 1.25 quarts/lb = 18.75 -> 19 quarts or 4 3/4 gal. Strike temp: target 169.8. Sparge vol: 3 1/4 gal. Pre-boil: 6.75 gal 1.040.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Harvest Amber]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/09/12/Harvest-Amber/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/09/12/Harvest-Amber</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brewed with homegrown Cascade hops.</p>

<h2>Grains</h2>

<ul>
<li>14 lbs American 2-Row Pale</li>
<li>1 lb Crystal 60</li>
<li>1 lb Victory</li>
</ul>


<h2>Hops</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 oz Homegrown Cascade, 90 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Homegrown Cascade, 60 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Homegrown Cascade, 15 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Homegrown Cascade, 5 mins</li>
<li>2 oz Homegrown Cascade, dry-hopped 4 weeks in secondary</li>
</ul>


<h2>Process</h2>

<p>Mash for 1 hour, don't remember the temperature. Sparge with enough water to collect 7.5 gallons, with pre-boil gravity of 1.055. Boiled down to 6 gallons (I think), with starting gravity of 1.066.</p>

<p>I boiled this one for 90 minutes in an attempt to get some better hop
utilization. I think I boiled 7.5 gallons down to 6 (rather than my
usual 5.5) because I expected to lose some volume during dry-hopping.</p>

<p>Primary fermentation for 2 weeks, then secondary fermentation for 4
more, dry hopping with homegrown Cascade hops.</p>

<h2>Notes</h2>

<p>This one tastes pretty good, although it's not nearly as hoppy as I
was hoping for. I guess the homegrown hops weren't very strong. I was
expecting them to be around 6% AA, but who knows what they really
are. Nice mouthfeel. There's a little bit of the caramel/banana off
flavor that showed up in the Belgian strong ale, but it's not nearly
as dominant here. This is not exactly what I was going for, but still
very enjoyable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Belgian Strong Ale]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/08/20/Belgian-Strong-Ale/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/08/20/Belgian-Strong-Ale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I originally wanted to make this and add our homegrown raspberries in
the secondary fermenter, but there ended up being enough going on with
the beer that I thought the berries would be too much.</p>

<p>This one has some undesireable off flavors. Not sure how to describe
it. Maybe caramel, banana. Pretty sweet, not much hop bitterness and
really no hop flavor or aroma at all. It seemed to get a bit worse
with a couple months of aging too. I suspect the off flavors may be
due to fermenting at higher temperatures. Also, this is the first
batch where I didn't use filtered water; I just let the water sit in
buckets overnight to let the chlorine evaporate.</p>

<h2>Grains</h2>

<ul>
<li>16 lbs Belgian 2-Row Pale</li>
<li>1 lb Biscuit malt</li>
<li>1 lb Special B malt</li>
<li>1 lb Belgian Candi Sugar, 45 (not mashed)</li>
<li>1 lb Belgian Candi Sugar 90 (not mashed)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Hops</h2>

<ul>
<li>2 oz Styrian Goldings, 90 mins</li>
</ul>


<h2>Process</h2>

<p>Mash for 1 hour at around 152 &deg;. Sparge with enough water to collect 7 gallons. Pre-boil gravity was 1.060. Boil for 90 minutes, adding Styrian Goldings hops for 90 minutes. Boiled down to 5.5 gallons at 1.084 starting gravity.</p>

<p>Fermented with Wyeast Trappist High Gravity yeast, I think, at a
pretty high temperature; maybe 75 &deg; or higher. Left in primary for
a few weeks and then secondary for maybe a month more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smoked Rye Porter]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/07/11/Smoked-Rye-Porter/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/07/11/Smoked-Rye-Porter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Brewed for the 2011 Iron Brewer competition sponsored by
<a href="keystonehomebrew.com">Keystone Homebrew Supply</a> and
<a href="thefarmerscabinet.com">The Farmers' Cabinet</a>. The idea was that they
give you a "secret ingredient", and you have a few months to make a
beer involving that ingredient. The secret ingredient was about 2lbs
of cherry wood smoked rye. I picked it up at The Farmers' Cabinet in
June. It smelled great; sort of like a campfire. This is actually what
made me decide to switch to all-grain brewing.</p>

<p>Made it into the "elite eight" out of 48 entries. This one was really
good. Very dark color, with a hint of red. Smooth, creamy mouthfeel,
maybe due to the rye. Hops are nicely balanced. Not too much smoke;
maybe should have used the rye sooner.</p>

<h2>Grains</h2>

<ul>
<li>11 lbs English 2 Row Pale</li>
<li>1.75 lbs Cherry Wood Smoked Rye</li>
<li>1 lb Crystal 60</li>
<li>1/2 lb Chocolate Malt</li>
</ul>


<h2>Hops</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 oz Northern Brewer, 60 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Willamette, 30 mins</li>
<li>1 oz Willamette, 15 mins</li>
</ul>


<h2>Process</h2>

<p>Mash all grains for 1 hour at 152&deg;.  Sparge with enough water to collect 6.5 gallons. Pre-boil gravity was 1.044. Bring to a boil, add hops according to schedule above. Cool and pitch yeast. Starting gravity was 1.058, final was 1.019.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ESB]]></title>
    <link href="http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/07/04/ESB/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://mdelaurentis.github.com/blog/2011/07/04/ESB</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was my first all-grain batch. It was very light in body and
alcohol. Probably should have used more grains.</p>

<h2>Grains</h2>

<ul>
<li>8 lbs English 2 Row Pale</li>
<li>1/2 lbs Crystal 60</li>
</ul>


<h2>Hops</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 oz  Northern Brewer, 60 mins</li>
<li>3/4 oz East Kent Golding, 30 mins</li>
<li>3/4 oz East Kent Golding, 15 mins</li>
</ul>


<p>60 minute boil</p>

<p>Pre-boil: 6.5 gal, 1.029 sg
Post-boil: 5.5 gal, 1.036 sg
Final: 1.017 sg</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
